Gibson .O. Ekezie

ekeziegibson@gmail.com, Blog, GitHub, LinkedIn, Twitter

Meticulous DevOps Engineer with a background in Linux Administration and 3+ years of experience designing, implementing, automating, and deploying secure cloud-based solutions. I am intent on cost-effective operational efficiency while enhancing system integration. I am a team player, who is always open to new challenges that involve learning new technologies and improving my cloud-native skills.

AWS Experience

- AWS Infrastructure Automation- CloudFormation, Terraform, Ansible
- AWS Core Services EC2, CloudWatch, Parameter Store, Systems Manager, S3, CLI, Cost Explorer, SQS, SNS, Auto-Scaling Groups,
- AWS Networking Services VPC, Security Groups, Subnets, ELB, Route 53, Cloudfront, Transit Gateway, VPN, Privatelink
- AWS Devops Services CodePipeline, CodeBuild, codecommit
- AWS Security Services Certificate Manager, IAM, KMS, AWS Config
- AWS Serverless Services Lambda
- AWS Database Services RDS, ElastiCache
- AWS Container Services ECS, EKS

Azure Experience

- Azure Infrastructure Automation- ARM Templates, Terraform, Ansible
- Azure Core Services Virtual machines, virtual machine scale sets, Storage account,
 CLI, Azure pricing calculator, Azure Event Hub, Azure service bus, App service
- Azure Networking Services Azure Virtual Network, Network Security Groups, Subnets, Application gateway, App service domain, dns zones, Azure frontdoor, Virtual network Gateway, VPN, Privatelink, Private endpoint
- Azure Devops Services azure pipeline, azure repos, azure boards
- Azure Security Services Key Vault, azure monitor, application insight, Azure AD, Sentinel, Log Analytics
- Azure Serverless Services Azure functions, Azure Logic Apps, Automation accounts
- Azure Database Services Azure SQL, Azure Cache of Redis, Azure Synaspe, Azure Data factory
- Azure Container Services Azure Kubernetes Service, container Instance

Technical Skills

- Programming Languages Python, HTML, CSS, golang
- Scripting Language: Bash, Powershell
- AWS: Identity and access management, Image Builder, EC2, S3, RDS, Route 53, VPC, ELB, Autoscaling, CloudFront, CloudWatch, SNS, SQS and Lambda.
- Azure: Azure AD, Express route, Azure Virtual Machine, Storage accounts, App service plan, function app, Azure sql databases, Web apps, Load Balancer, Vnet and Azure service Bus.
- Linux: Managing users, configuring services, Apache-PHP-MYSQL setup, server configuration, Virtual host setup, network troubleshooting, using SSH to connect to remote hosts and general troubleshooting.
- Containers Docker, Fargate, Kubernetes, Helm, Elastic Container Service (ECS), Azure Kubernetes Service.
- MS Server: Windows Server 2019, IIS Server, STIGS, STIG viewer.
- Databases PostgreSQL, Oracle, MongoDB, MySQL, MS SQL, Server, DynamoDB, Athena, Redshift
- Tooling, Services & Libraries Jenkins, Git, GitHub, Github actions, Nexus, Ansible, Prometheus, Nginx, Terraform, Azure DevOps, Microservices, Packer, aws-nuke

Certifications

- Microsoft Azure Security Engineer Associate
- Microsoft Azure DevOps Engineer
- Microsoft Azure Administrator
- Cisco Certified Network Associate
- Certified Kubernetes Administrator
- AWS Certified Solutions Architect-Associate
- AWS Certified DevOps Engineer Professional
- AWS Certified Security Specialty
- Certified Kubernetes security specialist

Education

Cloud And DevOps: Continuous Transformation

Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) Professional Education

Bachelor of Science: Biological Science

Work Experience

04/2021 - 01/2024

DevOps Engineer: Remote(contract) **ThanosConsulting**

- Designed high-level architectural diagrams for infrastructure provisioning on AWS and Azure cloud.
- Built Jenkins Pipeline to automate the building and deployment of java and c# artifacts.
- Developed Terraform automation scripts to deploy resources to AWS and Azure
- Created Packer script to build customized AMI images for Windows and Linux.
- Implemented AWS pipeline using a build script and AWS codecommit for version control.
- Collaborated with the Networking team to implement cross-account VPC endpoints and privatelink connectivity between an Ec2 instance and an RDS database.
- Developed ARM templates to deploy virtual machines and invoke PowerShell user-data script.
- Worked on developing Ansible playbooks for the Cloud Automation and Infrastructure provisioning, creating the test environments with required configurations
- Researched and evaluated Azure public cloud edge computing latency benefits.
- Migrated Windows and Linux servers from Azure to Hyper-V virtualized environment.
- Applied STIGs to windows Server depending on organization's preferences.
- Collaborated with the development team to perform migration of mainframe application to Azure and AWS.
- Deployed ECS Fargate cluster and AWS Transfer Family using Terraform.
- Implemented Terraform workspace to manage multiple instances of configuration with different state files.

AWS DevOps Engineer: Remote **Cloutra**

- Designed high-level architectural diagrams for infrastructure provisioning on AWS.
- Developed automation scripts for AWS resources deployment using cloudformation.
- Created step-by-step documentation for the Implementation of cloud labs in AWS sandbox accounts.
- Built CI/CD pipeline to build and deploy a python program using AWS codepipeline.
- Automated the deployment of secure landing zones for each cloud lab use-case using cloudformation.
- Created Service principal policies for AWS organization in a multi-account environment.
- Automated the implementation of complex managed policies, roles, and IAM permission boundaries using cloudformation.
- Created IAM Passrole to provide least privileged access to AWS services.
- Created secrets to store API keys using AWS Secret Manager.
- Implemented selective AWS resource deletion using AWS-nuke.

06/2022 - 02/2023

Azure Support Engineer: Remote(contract) **Ros**

- Built Azure DevOps Pipeline to automate the deployment of infrastructure using Terraform.
- Developed Terraform modules to automate the deployment of virtual machine instances in Azure and Azure Kubernetes cluster.
- Troubleshooted VPC network issues using Azure network watcher.
- Created powershell scripts to configure Windows virtual Machines after deployment.
- Managed terraform state files remotely to ensure compliance with company policies and detect drift in infrastructure.
- Collaborated with the development team to implement Azure DevOps pipelines that deployed Snowflake tables using Terraform.
- Implemented version control on Terraform scripts using Azure Repos.
- Designed high-level architectural diagrams for infrastructure provisioning on azure cloud.

Azure Administrator: Remote(contract) **Moneymart**

- Renewed self-signed certificates for Azure automation accounts.
- Administered access control on multiple Azure subscriptions by managing Azure roles and policies.
- Implemented and maintained the monitoring and alerting of production and corporate servers/storage using Azure monitor and log analytics.
- Added project users to the Azure account with multifactor authentication enabled and least privilege permissions.
- Developed virtual networks for workload isolation.
- Created Service accounts for secure application access.
- Built compute infrastructure on Azure manually through the Azure portal and automated the deployment of Azure Storage service using Terraform.
- Implemented scripts with Power Shell for Azure automation Run books.
- Worked extensively on configuring, installing and migrating VM Servers.
- Configured Windows server features and deployed applications using PowerShell scripting.
- Implemented secure connectivity to private storage accounts from the on-prem network through private endpoints.

01/2021 - current

Devops Freelancer: On-Request

- Provided high level architectural diagrams for infrastructure set up on azure cloud and aws.
- Built azure devops Pipeline to automate the deployment of infrastructure using terraform.
- Resolved Azure devops pipeline issues.
- Performed automation using tools like terraform, ansible, arm templates and packer.
- Worked on creating Terraform modules to launch instances in Azure & automated process of creation of resources is Azure using Terraform.
- Experience in dealing with windows Azure services Virtual Networks, Virtual Machines, Resource Groups, VPN, Load Balancing, Auto Scaling, Azure monitoring, Traffic Manager.
- Resolved VPC connectivity issues
- ARM templates writing, setup automation for resources provisioning (Azure PowerShell
- Used terraform to deploy infrastructure and managed state files remotely to ensure compliance with policies requested and detect drift in infrastructure.

- Performed design, deployment, configuration, and maintenance of scalable Cloud infrastructure with an intense focus on Quality, Security, high availability and fail over functionality.
- Configuring windows server features and deploying applications using PowerShell scripting.

05/2020 - 11/2020

DevOps & Infrastructure Engineer (Intern)

Bincom Dev, Lagos Nigeria

- Built compute infrastructure on AWS from the AWS console.
- Built S3 buckets and managed policies for S3 buckets and used S3 bucket and Glacier for storage and backup on AWS.
- Used Jenkins pipelines to drive all Microservices builds
- Configured and maintained Jenkins to implement the CI process and integrated the tool with Maven to schedule the builds.
- Created IAM custom policies.
- Configured LAMP stack on Linux server.
- Used AWS Lambda, Python and AWS SDK Boto3 to automate the running and stop of EC2 instances in the Dev Environment to ensure that cost is effectively optimized.
- Planned and Implemented migration of On-Prem servers to EC2 in AWS Cloud.
- Wrote CloudFormation Scripts to automate the creation of the production stack
- Build, improve, maintain, support infrastructure as code.
- Effectively handled the integrating AWS services: EC2, S3, VPC Endpoints, VPC PrivateLink, VPC Peering, Transit VPC, Network Protocol, Subnetting (Private and Public), IPsec, VPN, Route53, ELB, Auto scaling, SQS, SNS, IAM, DynamoDB, Lambda, Amazon Kinesis, CloudFront, Cloud Formation, CloudWatch, CloudTrail, internet Gateway to have a well architecture framework.
- Implemented processes and procedures to improve overall efficiency in operations.
- monitored AWS resources using Cloud Watch.